Speaker: Jack Horton lives in San José in Costa Rica,
where he teaches computer science in a secondary school.
When he arrived in Costa Rica, the first thing that Jack noticed was
how incredibly friendly the people are.
Jack says the “ticos” – as they’re called in Costa Rica
– are much friendlier than people in his home country.
They always say buenos días to you even if they don’t know you.
If something’s good, like a beautiful day or a good meal, the ticos say pura vida.
It literally means “pure life.”
But Jack thinks it really means “things are great.”
One thing that can be difficult for foreigners is that the sense of time
is completely different in Costa Rica.
The Costa Ricans call it “tico time.”
If there is an appointment at seven in the evening, ticos probably leave home at seven o’clock.
But everyone knows it's OK not to arrive on time, and it's not a problem.
Another thing that surprised Jack was the weather.
He thought Costa Rica was hot and sunny all the time.
That’s true in the dry season, and the temperature’s about 77 degrees all year round,
but in the rainy season, especially in September and October,
it rains heavily for about two hours a day.
Everyone told Jack that the scenery was beautiful in Costa Rica.
But it was even more beautiful than he expected,
with incredible animals, birds, trees — and volcanoes.
Some of the volcanoes are active and smoke quietly,
and then suddenly there’s a big bang and they start erupting.
Jack was very frightened the first time it happened.
At first, Jack thought life in Costa Rica was going to be cheap.
But in fact, Jack found out that food is expensive, especially imported food.
The only thing that’s cheap is fruit, vegetables, and the wonderful, wonderful coffee.
And the fruit and vegetables are very different from those in Jack’s home country.
One day, he went to a market and he didn’t recognize any of the fruit.
Jack likes San José.
Some people think it can be dangerous, but Jack doesn’t feel that it is.
He says it's true that some of the roads are terrible,
but in general, he really loves it in Costa Rica.